Everything you've been told about value
investing is a lie, and I can prove it
with real back tests. I'm a PhD
physicist, and building models that
don't lie to me is my actual day job.
So, I built a code that automates value
investing to choose stocks that are
cheap compared to their true value, and
it did not work. But, through my GitHub
repository, a lot of you pointed out
some key issues in the back test. So,
I'm going to rebuild this incorporating
your comments to find out if value
investing actually works.
Value investing isn't some fringe idea.
In fact, it might be the most tested
idea in the history of finance. The
concept is pretty simple. The value of a
company can fluctuate depending on
public opinion and market sentiment, but
the company has value of which can be
measured in different ways, for example,
by looking at its revenue growth or
debt. These fundamentals can be put
together to calculate what a company is
truly [music] worth, the intrinsic
value. And when the market value, or
what it's currently trading at, falls
far below the intrinsic value, we say
that the company is trading at a
discount. We buy that stock and see
outsized returns as the market value and
public sentiment changes and the price
recovers back to what it should be. This
concept has inspired a lot of YouTube
videos, some of which are created by
very educated people, even with PhDs,
and I've always wondered why nobody has
back tested this to clearly state if it
works or not. So, when one of them tells
you it can't really be back tested,
that's a lie. A strategy can always be
back tested because a strategy is just a
list of decisions, and a list of
decisions is exactly what a coding back
test is there to provide. These are the
same excuses that some day traders use
to keep their audience buying their
courses so they can make money off their
audience and not day trading. But,
people still believe in value investing.
The value investing Reddit thread has
over 700,000 members, and people in my
comments genuinely believe in the
strategy. So, if it does work, then a
simple back test should show above
market returns. Otherwise, we should all
just buy the S&P and go to bed. In my
last video, I built a value investing
bot that used a Graham method with
company earnings, an estimate of the
growth rate, and AAA bond yields to
calculate a stock's intrinsic value. We
then validated this by hand. Also, thank
you to the commenter that suggested I do
that to confirm that the model was
indeed making correct calculations. But,
it underperformed a buy and hold
strategy. There were a bunch of comments
that correctly pointed out some fatal
flaws in the algorithm that I absolutely
must fix because value investing maybe
does work, and I'm just being a negative
Nancy. The sharpest critique of all was
that my benchmark or what I was
comparing our strategy to was super
unfair. My stomach sunk when you simply
removed the companies you couldn't
calculate the fair value from your
market portfolio. Lol. I had skipped
stocks that I couldn't value with the
Graham model. Maybe there wasn't enough
data or the earnings reports were all
zero, so I couldn't actually calculate
an intrinsic value. But, instead of
dropping them from the backtest, I
actually left them in, which is
definitely a big mistake. This is super
unfair because those stocks could by
chance performed really well, and I
wasn't even allowing my strategy to
choose them if it wanted to. So, if I
can't calculate an intrinsic value for a
particular ticker, I should drop that
ticker from the benchmark. Now, before
viewing the results of this improvement
in the backtest, we should see where we
left off from before. I'm using a
discount factor of 50% here. So, we're
only going to buy super cheap stocks.
The green line is our value-based
strategy, and the red line is what we're
comparing to, which is an equal
weighting of stocks from our
reconstructed S&P 500 membership list.
The white line is just the actual S&P
500, and you can see that I actually did
a terrible job at recreating it, and I
clearly have a bunch of survivorship
bias since my recreated S&P 500 list is
actually [music] beating the actual S&P
500. Anyways, it seems that between 2000
and 2002, the value-based strategy shown
in green actually did really, really
well. Well, sort of. Up until the point
that stocks recovered to their intrinsic
value, the algorithm then sold them all,
and we basically found no cheap stocks
for the next two decades. The
value-based strategy achieved an
annualized return of 0.9%
and our S&P 500 membership list, or the
buy and hold strategy, achieved 8.6%.
So, this is pretty bad, but how does it
fare with our improvement? Let's now
look at the back test where we remove
stocks we can't quantify with the
intrinsic value formula. Recall that our
fix should only change the benchmark in
red since we're dropping companies that
we can't calculate a Graham value for.
So, this will have no effect on the
intrinsic value back test itself, but
only the comparison that we're making.
And because of that, the value strategy
returns stayed the same at 0.9%
annualized, but the baseline was 8.55%.
So, it actually didn't really change
that much. But, I mean, this is a better
back test, right? Anyways, let's move
on. Last time, I hard-coded a 50%
discount to make sure that we are buying
super cheap stocks. And two of you
pointed out that it's a little bit
arbitrary.
>> Try other range, for example, instead of
buying discount is greater than 50%, try
discount within 0 50% or instead of is
greater than 90%, try other 10% range.
>> So, instead, we could rank stocks by how
discounted they are and then just buy
the cheapest. And at first, it sort of
looks like the strategy is working until
it fails terribly. Yeah, I don't even
really know what to say about this one.
It just didn't work. The total return of
the cheapest stock over this time
horizon was minus 92.9%
or minus 9.46% [music]
annualized. But, there is a bit of a
trap here. Manually tweaking the
discount until it looks good is
effectively just hand-operated
overfitting, and the cheapest stock is
also not always the best one. There
could be a systematic flaw in the
company we've selected. So, how about
this? Let's try every single discount
factor. And here you go. These are the
returns as a function of the discount
factor. There are literally no strategy
returns shown in green that beat our
baseline shown in red. [music] And also,
yes, just a reminder that we are beating
the S&P 500 over this time horizon,
[music] but slow down. We're actually
comparing to the red line because that's
the return of the tickers in our
database. That's the benchmark. The top
technical comment in my last video said
that equity curves alone are not enough
and I completely agree.
>> Please compare some sort of performance
metrics.
>> We need to show the risk-adjusted
performance of the strategy.
Specifically, we need to use the Sortino
ratio. Now, the Sortino ratio measures
the risk-adjusted return of an
investment portfolio, but unlike other
metrics, it only penalizes downside
volatility. And yeah, I know this sounds
super boring, but I promise it's
actually rather straightforward and is a
concept you can apply to everything in
your life. Now, you may wonder, why do
we care about risk-adjusted returns?
>> Boring.
>> I only care about the returns, right? I
mean, that's the only thing that matters
to me. And at first, that's what I
thought, too, but it's not quite true.
Because in making a high return, there
was some risk involved in that trade.
Now, let's say for example that you
invest $1 million
and there's a 50% chance that you see a
100% return. So, then it becomes $2
million,
but there's also a 50% chance that you
lose it all. Let's say that you come out
of the other end with a favorable trade
and you do get that 100% return. [music]
Congrats, but you can't neglect the fact
that you took a 50% chance of losing all
of your money. You tell yourself that
you will keep betting your winnings
because the first time you did it, you
got a 100% return. It was great. That
same trade over many trades would
guarantee that you do lose all of your
money because the single time that you
land on the other side of that 50%
chance, your portfolio goes to zero.
Even though you won and your return was
100%, the risk-adjusted return of that
trade is actually minus 100% because
you're statistically guaranteed, if you
take that bet enough, to lose
everything. So, we should always factor
in risk into our investments, which is
usually characterized by market
volatility. Our Graham strategy has a
Sortino ratio of 0.171.
The S&P 500 buy and hold is 0.545.
And our benchmark of S&P constituents is
0.666.
Oh lord. Our strategy is roughly three
times worse on a risk-adjusted basis
than simply buying and holding, which is
pretty bad. And over a rolling one-year
window, the strategy beats the S&P
Sortino only about 34% of the time. This
strategy only worked well during the
2008 market crash, and that basically
tells you nothing. And I'm not saying
that this will never work. I'm just
saying that the current strategy is not
sufficient. But, I encourage you to
leave comments below describing what you
could test or what I'm getting wrong,
and then we can try to implement this in
a future video and improve the
algorithm. So, if value investing
doesn't work anymore, why do people keep
making videos about it implying that it
does? Now, I'm not a drama channel, so
I'm going to stay clear of calling
people out, but I have a couple of
theories. Firstly, it's that the decades
of genuine success stories like Buffett
give this method real credibility. It's
also the perfect thing to sell people on
and just sort of make sense. Stocks are
cheap, and you should try to buy them
cheap before they recover. And finally,
you can't easily disprove it yourself
unless you're degenerates like me and
you and test it with code like we just
did. So, my honest take is that value
investing isn't a scam. It's just that
the efficient market theory has caught
up to it, and it's up to us to create
different methodologies to find gaps
that are present today. So, if you find
something that looks interesting, I'll
test it. We live in a new age of
investing where complexity is scaling
exponentially, meaning old opportunities
fade and new opportunities are
introduced. Take care, and I'll see you
guys in the next one.